[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
so welcome to the store everyone um for
those of you who have not been here
before this is a sense maker in
residence series uh with starring peter
wang
this is the last session
it's a part uh four to four four parts
and uh yeah the theme is mental models
and
uh this is about the mental models peter
uses to navigate the complexities of
life
and each session there's like a
constellation of models he presents us
that are
related and interesting ways so how's
this going to work is peter's going to
present
uh his uh thoughts and if you have
any um questions throw them in the chat
i'll call you on mute yourself if you
want me to read on your behalf let me
know
and i will do so that being said peter
good morning my friend good morning
thank you sorry i'm running a little bit
late this morning
um and thank you everyone for for coming
and i'm looking forward to this one
um let me go ahead and start presenting
here
share screen uh
share and i guess i can go
play
come on you can do a keynote can you
guys see that anyone see it
good somehow when i go full screen i
lose my
mouse but that's all right um okay so
this last one i will talk about
communications
and mimetics and all things not all
things but several topics around
around that complex of of uh of things
and um but uh but to start with i will
recap what i've talked about the first
three so on the very first one
uh i did the very first session i did
the metaphysics of quality
and talking about how to look at things
instead of as
atomic separated objects um
static we should instead see them as
overlapping
waves of patterns and we simply assign
names to certain
sets of waves or wave fronts even and
that there is a tear
according to the metaphysical says
metaphysics of quality there's sort of a
tearing
or a layering of of waves of of
different
characteristics and there's a physical
layer of biological social and
intellectual layer
and every single one of these layers the
waves and the patterns there seem to
push
whenever there's excess energy they seem
to push upwards uh so to speak they try
to
uh they strive for some greater order
something that
that the author of the metaphysics of
quality named robert persig something
that he called
dynamic quality um so i encourage people
to think less about
atomized things billiard balls knocking
around in space
and more about everything being super
positional
uh the second stoa session i did i
talked about the relationships
and how we should look again to the same
theme instead of looking at
relationships as
sort of a dashed or dotted line
connecting these
these billiard balls or or atomized
objects
we should instead think about inverting
that and see that the relational
stresses relationships expectations of
them
and the interactions actually create
these locuses or loci
which we then give identity to uh
whether that identity is ourselves
whether that identity
is what something we might call the
government or france or
our our marriage or whatever um
that's to start viewing objects not in
terms of
their hard boundaries but in terms of
the relationship pressures associated
with them
and to try to view the world from a
perspective of relationships being
primary
and identity being fluid and emergent
from all these pipes of identity
plugging into the same spot
and then the third one last time i
talked about a set of viewing objects
and relationships being static to
instead view
everything as having a four-dimensional
nature i talked about the ship of
theseus
about how uh many ques so-called
questions and paradoxes
of identity and philosophy are really
rooted in
you know not a problem in the real world
but a problem with the the framing that
we look at things in
and specifically if we choose to look at
things as static objects
um maybe imbued with something we call
energy or potential
that then we get very confused about
identity and the nature of things
but if we instead view everything as
being wavefronts that are always or
waves that are always
evolving in time then there isn't really
so many of these paradoxes and problems
uh it does then lead to other questions
like who am i what am i if i'm just a
bunch of overlapping wavefronts and
expectations
but that's that's actually a more
tangible or more attractive problem in
my mind
so the first one is to stop looking at
the world as atomized objects but look
at the superpositions of things
the second is to look at relationships
as primary
and the third is to think about time
always think about the temporal
dimension not as an afterthought but as
a foundational part
of reality
and if we were to smoosh some of these
together we can take the metaphysical
quality
look at the layerings of individuals or
objects or whatever
and then and actually see how all of
these proceed forward in time maybe at
different rates
and the shearing of these things
actually creates stresses and create
some of the problems that we see in the
world
so let me go back and recap this a
different way
in the physical layer in physical
reality we tend to think about objects
as being hard demarcated things um
we tend to think of time as merely
potential right this is the big problem
with newtonian physics uh
for those who are not uh physicists on
this call
the the general problem that we have
with uh with things like newtonian
physics
is that there is nothing called the or
the arrow of time
so all the math that you write to
describe a system of particles moving or
you know bouncing off each other doing
whatever you can run time forwards or
backwards there's no reason why they
have to go one way or another
and only with thermodynamics do we then
introduce something like
an arrow of time why systems must evolve
in a particular way
so in that kind of physics time is
really viewed as potential you have
objects they've got mass
there's a force and there's energy but
all of those forces and energies are all
potential really
the object is the static object and then
the relationships between them we might
say there's an attractive force there's
a repulsive force between these charges
right these are all seen as potentials
and the inferred by the temporal
coupling
if we were to unfreeze time and watch
these things evolve in time
we can say yes there was a force the
force is what explains these things
spiraling around each other
or you know collapsing into each other
or whatever so that's a very physical
view of the world
things are demarcated and anchored in
space
a biological view of the world the layer
of biology
is when that layer of description ceases
to be the
the most useful we won't talk about
whether it's true or not true
we should talk about utility in
prediction and describing phenomena
right
and so the physical layer descriptions
cease to be useful
when we start having objects that can
have memory that seem
to evolve in time and as they evolve in
time they seem to
remember what happened to them in the
past and respond to that so there's a
what we call a path dependency
right you can't just say well what is
the uh future path
of a of a
bacterium in this petri dish right the
physicist has no answer for you
because it could be any number of things
but the biologist says well where is the
sugar
right well i'll tell you guess what that
bacteria is probably gonna move in the
direction of the sugar
or sort of move towards the light or do
whatever these systems have
these are we tend to think about things
as systems of interaction they have
memory both of themselves and of their
interaction with others
and time now becomes a fundamental
aspect of a biological description
of the world um and the cadence of
moreover
the cadence of interaction between
things is essential so when we talk
about
a biological system like all of us are
biological systems we try to analyze our
cellular structure
and we look at the cellular pathways and
all of the various kind of biochemical
sort of things
that happens on the order of
milliseconds or you know microseconds
when we talk about us as people things
take on the order of
decades right so the time scale the
cadence of interaction
you have to eat and sleep on a daily
basis you know these are the kinds of
things we used to talk about biological
systems but the key difference here
between biological physical
in my view is that in the biological
world we we talk about objects that have
memory and generally they are systems of
interaction
and we cannot again you can't talk about
memory without talking about time
so these have there's a strict temporal
aspect to or not strict but there's a
necessary temporal aspect to talking
about this
um no one talks about so to make that
just a little bit more concrete
we don't talk about people as having
feeling a
a hunger force driving them like that's
that would be a useless description of a
person
because it's not like that it doesn't
like if you feel hungry you get more
hungry and then you do things because
you get hungry
as you get progressively hungrier you
know we we we sort of talk about
descriptions of systems
um and and the cadences and the temporal
evolution that way
and then then the next layer social
interaction
or the layer of social phenomena let's
say um
for me the important thing there is
recursion
and self-awareness so at that point
things are
social in nature when they are modeling
the behavior of others
and that and also there's some awareness
that others are modeling us
that's not necessary but it's one of the
dynamics certainly if we talk about
humans and other sort of uh more
advanced intelligence
intelligent animals or creatures on the
earth um there is a concept of a
self-image
um it's fascinating if you watch these
documentaries of first contact with
uncontacted tribes or under-contacted
tribes
uh when a tribe of of um
you know bush people let's call them
like that living in in like the forests
of papua new guinea or whatever
never seen a white man before when
they're first shown a mirror
and they see themselves it's just
fascinating the discovery of the
self-image
um and you watch like the the the the
the tribe leader
and then they passes around like the
kids are trying to pop in there and see
themselves
it's just absolutely fascinating to
watch the human animal discover
uh high fidelity self-image so um
so this this anyway recursion
self-awareness is what creates
the social interactions or makes the
social plane of phenomenology possible
and then lastly but not least of course
for this conversation today
or this discussion um the intellectual
plane
and and i i tend to characterize that as
the realm of pure subjectivity or
intersubjectivity
and it's not anchored to physical
reality all of us are anchored to
physical reality
uh this recording will probably
hopefully maybe
but this recording can absolutely um
have a far
longer life span than i ever do the
ideas this slide deck that i
that i made right in the last few days
the slide deck is more immortal than me
right so we might think wow you know
humans can become immortal by leaving a
legacy and you know setting up the
future generations and
you know putting sperm and egg together
and all these things it's like no
make a powerpoint make a pdf make a meme
and now you've touched immortality
because those things are untethered to
physical reality in a way that
the human embodied life can never really
be at least not until we you know get
brain upload
into the matrix or whatever so um
another way of looking at this um of
course our our favorite uh
uh our favorite man at the moment here
is marshall mcluhan
who says that in an electric in an era
of electric communications when we have
electricity conducting ideas
at the speed of light um i'll give you
guys a chance to read this
physical connectedness gives way to the
resonant bonds and gigantic open system
patterns
of electric information and it's really
important this last line the perception
of reality
now depends upon the structure of
information
um there's a small problem with that
statement which we'll get to later in
the in the
in the um presentation but nonetheless
this is somebody in the 60s identifying
that just
you know uh broadcast television and fm
radio
and um you know the these national
newspapers all of these kinds of things
are creating a reality
where the intersubjective the
intellectual plane
uh actually is is dominant
so today communications of medics this
all kind of sets us up then to talk
about communications and i would say
that probably most people
would think of communications uh in this
way that there's a
sender there's a receiver they
communicate via some kind of channel
there's messages
sometimes there's feedback and there's
noise in the in the channel um
but the sender has an encoding the
receiver has a decoding
um this is not an unfamiliar model of
communications if if any of us had to
sit down and take a quiz we'd probably
write something like this right
um but you know this is very much using
this object-oriented metaphysics it's
very much thinking about
sender and receiver as as separate as
thinking about this message as this
disembodied like piece of information or
data
flowing down a wire um
and john perry barlow had some
incredibly incredible you never would
expected a member of the grateful dead
to have
so much amazing memetic insights but he
is truly an amazing person
and he made this observation that
receiving
information is often as creative an act
as generating it
we often we should assign a value to
information based on its meaningfulness
which of course is defined within the
the
the subjectivity of the receiver
so this is really really a a
very different way of looking at it
because when you look at this picture of
communications
we tend to think about well the sender
has an idea
they got a message to send they put the
message in the bottle they float the
bottle
to the other person and they did all the
stuff the other person just has to
you know catch the bottle pop it open
you know find some light
and then like read the faded text and
that's all they got to do right and the
sending of the
messages is like where all the stuff
happens right authorship of course
authorship is is emphasized and and
glamorized
readership no one thinks about the act
of reading and the act of understanding
when you're reading
as being equal to that task and yet what
john perry barlow is saying
is that no actually reading
interpretation is
as creative and act as generating the
thing in the first place
maybe when we think about music this
becomes a little more accessible right
all of us know that to really enjoy i
mean everyone's got probably some pieces
of music they really enjoy
and and you know it's that to you know
the feeling of really listening to a
piece of music and really enjoying it
is different than just having a blasting
on the car when you're like driving
through rush hour traffic
when you really sit there and and feel
the music
or when you're if you if you go to um
music concert or if you go to rave
or you go and you dance to music right
that's that's an expression
receiving music but also transmitting at
the same time and acting at the same
time so
this this idea that receiving
information is a creative act it's maybe
not so foreign to us but most people i
would venture don't think about it in
this way
that the act of reception is is such an
important
um active thing and um
and so the the the meaning
that comes the meaning making between
the sender and the receiver in this act
of communication
that actually comes from the interaction
um
when nowadays with with uh so much
broadcast media um
we are so used to the idea of receiving
information as the thing we do
disembodied
from the transmission like someone
performed it somebody taped it somebody
edited it somebody added a bunch of
other crap to it
and then having been preaching
pre-digested it's blasted out over
airwaves and over fiber into our brains
into our eyeballs into our ears
and so um the act of reception
now is the is is really like we can
choose to receive it or interpret it
but but that's really where we get to
make our meaning we can't go back like i
can't go and talk
back to any of those people in fact
twitter's whole little
twitter's cool little social hack is to
give people the semblance of being able
to do so
right like barack obama tweets something
or donald trump tweets something
and then thousands of people tweet
responses to him
why he's not gonna read it right it's
absolutely
theater it's you're stabbing a voodoo
doll hoping that you're gonna talk to it
and you're
no you got a voodoo doll and the entire
act the entire
um uh performance there is to get you
engaged in listening to what the voodoo
doll has to say
not because the voodoo doll feels the
pain or the the transmitter of it has
anything to do with you
so we now in this electric well almost a
post-electric age at this point in the
in the um internet age we we are uh very
confused and upside down on this dynamic
right if you think about communication
originally started a tribal sense around
a campfire people talking back and forth
to each other
uh very point to point and kind of
tribal and then it became this mass
dissemination
uh and we're now just on the receiving
end of it so we're we're conditioned to
be receivers
just like with products you know so many
uniform products
vended to us by the um industrial system
that terminates at walmarts and costco's
and whatnot
we are trained to be consumers of
pre-fabricated pre-chew pre-digested
product
we are not we're not really set up or
encouraged to see ourselves as
interactors with artisans um who go who
work with artisans to define the bespoke
thing we need
so same thing with meaning making and
communication um
and so my contention is that we have to
give
users tools to establish agency in this
reception process this is one of my
biggest beefs of social media
is that it's it's a walled garden of
communications infrastructure that
terminates
in software and uis that are controlled
by a very tiny few
number of people facebook tells me what
things i get to see in my feed
twitter defines exactly how i see pieces
of content not just the order of things
in the feed
but how i even see the content that
quote retweets are not shown in line
that i see the number of likes and down
votes and whatever else
and like i'm exposed to content before i
get to choose who it is i want to hear
from
all of the millions of decisions around
the user interface
i have no choice in them i am basically
being force fed my eyeball like
clockwork orange style my eyeballs
propped open
and i'm given exactly this kind of
interaction mode
so the ability to do meaning making is
then
relegated to just in my brain my control
over attention
managing my own internal emotional
psychic energy and balance
while i'm sort of getting force-fed this
stuff in this manner right
so um the other piece of this then is if
any medium facilitates interaction
it has a very important and sometimes
subtle influence on the act of meaning
making
um the fact that twitter by default
allows makes all
accounts public and anyone can reply not
just people that follow you and
followers of followers right
the idea of a follower versus a
subscriber versus a mutual
these are all things just they're
software artifacts they're like sql
queries inside or i guess only sql but
they're queries inside the twitter
software and yet that completely defines
the landscape interaction
right these kinds of things in instagram
and facebook uh in snapchat
they get kids they facilitate
cyberbullying they create a medical
landscape that slides towards
uh towards anger and towards meanness
towards um
hostility and outrage so if we create
software if we create mediums if we
create socialization environments um
anything that we do that creates an
interaction for
um or creates a facility for interaction
um we actually are
deeply influencing the act of meaning
making and that's that's a real
that's something to be taken that's a
task to be taken not lightly
um and then lastly of course
understanding
what you're actually seeing is a
critical element that's that's often
overlooked in the um
in this effort to turn information into
a commodity this is this this is
a lot of words but what what john perry
barlow is saying there
is that when we take information if we
zoom out a little bit
and we'll slow down just one one second
here if we zoom out a little bit
and again think about communication not
as being a sender doing a bunch of stuff
to create a disembodied artifact called
uh a communication
or information and then they're pumping
it down a channel to a receiver
okay if we view things from that
perspective
we can't help but view information as a
disembodied artifact and the receiver as
being an
active passive receiver of crap if we
actually view communications as
necessarily an interaction
then we realize that so many of our
communications infrastructures today
are like factory farms force-feeding a
bunch of pigs
it's not actually facilitating meaning
making and understanding
so if we look at the world through the
lens of senders creating content piping
out to receivers
then we necessarily overlook the
importance of
the receiver having time space context
and opportunity
to make sense to understand
and that's why i mean this is this is
this is a little cherry on top of
sense maker in residence why sense
making is a term you know sort of a
geeky term so many of us are starting to
use more more we'd want to get it
popularized
in the vernacular because it is it is um
you are not consumers you are not
recipients of content
you are sense makers desperately
aching and hungering for interaction
mediums
in which you can do better sense making
and those interaction mediums
must necessarily for their if they're
they're good at doing that if they're
if they support you in doing that if
they are if they support you
having good sense making then they will
necessarily strive to put you
in uh i guess what jordan likes to call
right relationship with other humans and
sense makers and together
then you can have a collective
intelligence otherwise you're just
a pig being force-fed a bunch of content
and of course you're not gonna have a
chance to make sense of the world of
course you won't
have understanding because that's not
what the force-feeding pipe is
optimizing for
right it's homogenized product
disseminated to a lot of different
things
and hopefully it tastes like food you
know that's kind of
the the embed in this last sentence
that's that's what i read in it and and
and
barlow wrote this decades ago decades
ago guys just absolutely genius
but um the other thing that i would say
tying to this this is not something he
said was something that i say
is that real information is
non-rivalrous
real information is generative real
information if we call it information
um it's it's um it's an act of sense
making
that is generative it is not scarce
ironically
bandwidth and attention are scarce right
there's only even if you have a
thick bundle of fiber like this going
under the sea
there's still finite bandwidth to it and
your attention every single person's
attention is scarce
but if we actually create information
if we actually make goods do good sense
making with each other
that is an anti-rival risk uh
anti-scarce
thing so another
way i would like to um oh there's an
empty bullet point there
let me take one sip of tea
before launching the next point which is
um another way to think about this
um this concept that the receiver
is um not just a passive receiver the
communication is not just the simple
model of a tube you know and uh and a
receiver and a transmitter
um the medium itself is a is an
important part
of the communications um making
communications possible
and i would just pose this question for
you a little thought experiment in the
morning here
which one of these things is transparent
which one of these things is opaque
not a hard question but many of you may
suspect a trick question right
because the brick wall is clearly opaque
and then the and a glass window is
clearly transparent
and so we use terms like transparency or
opacity
as properties of the medium right so
this is you know and in fact
it's it's we when we talk about oh um
you know the leadership of this company
is being transparent
or we want a transparent political
process we use that
as an attribute as almost an objective
attribute
a physical attribute of the thing itself
but the thing that's lost in that
is that transparency is entirely a
property of the relationship between the
receiving apparatus
and the signal so the brick wall is
actually quite transparent to radio
frequencies
you can stand inside a brick house with
a with an fm receiver and listen to
radio all day long
right your cell phone works through
brick because if it didn't
i mean it's a little bit attenuated but
not like if you were on the side of a
copper wall
right so um transparency
right this is this is just a simple
statement and then you might say well
okay peter if you're so clever what
about glass
well glass is transparent to us glasses
of course transparent to radio waves
but if you're looking at things in the
infrared i may heat that glass up to
you know 150 degrees fahrenheit and then
an infrared camera on the other side
sees just a sheet of red
there's nothing or a sheet of blue or
sheet like it's just completely opaque
and you can have two people five people
on the other side of that wall or on the
other side the glass
and the infrared camera would not be
able to see anything
because by heating the glass up to a
certain temperature the infrared camera
now human body temperatures are below
the the thermal threshold or the
below the noise floor so yeah you can
make glass
opaque as well it's opaque to infrared
um
and actually had a cop uh who was
talking to me about this where they
wanted to
have like they wanted to be able to use
like night vision equipment
and more and more of the modern night
vision equipment is uh thermal imaging
and the problem is when you use a
thermal imaging night vision thing from
inside a cop car
the glass is completely opaque because
your body heat of the car makes the
glass
opaque and so i was showing him a
different kind of night vision device
that i had
which can see what you see through it so
again
um even our intuitions are some of the
stuff right it it
serves to confound the topic of
transmission
of communications and so um the the
thing to understand that
why why brick walls and glass what does
that do with anything well
what this has to do with is that
everything is both a medium and a
transmitter
you and i are of course all transmitters
i'm doing more of the transmitting in
this call so far
but um but we're also mediums we're also
memory loaded cells that bounce around
and resonate with messages and then send
them off
like we're all like little dangling
church bells right
thousands millions of church bells and
when one rings it causes rings and all
of the others as well
uh with a little bit of lag so this is
this is the thing to understand
that everything is medium and
transmitter and when we talk about
opacity
transmis uh transparency we're actually
looking at it kind of 90 degrees off or
45 degrees off we need to tilt our
thinking
into conductivity and susceptibility to
re-transmit
um and yeah i said memory is this
phenomena of a medium now all of a
sudden taking on a four dimensional
characteristic
and so this is really interesting
because if you can view media mediums
themselves
as having a temporal extent you know
even an impulse thing something that
only happens once
the memory of it because the medium has
memory
it actually turns it into a different
kind of object it turns it into almost a
biological object because it has
because the medium itself has that
nature of of of shearing the thing
across time smoothing it over time and
integrating over time
so the other thing that happens of
course is that all
media really it changes as we pass
messages through it
it changes as it supports and
facilitates interaction
and of course it warps the message that
it conducts there's always degradation
and transmutation
um and nowadays especially with social
media and with
so many of our online communications
being conducted through
applications and software that are
um that that are so like they're not
actually communications media right
they just give the illusion of being
communications media and it's almost a
happy accident they do that
they're really designed to be attention
hijacking systems
that modify and modulate our thinking um
and run faster ooda loops around our
attention
so um but but even even if we use
something more like less sinister like
email
right um even the medium of email
changes the messages that are conducted
through
it we have to linearize things we have
to put things into the format and then a
lot of context is lost
you know so so as these things transmit
any kind of medium as it transmits
messages um the medium itself
transforms what is what is intelligible
uh within it
so i i take a pause there and say that
there's sort of a
a number of different directions we can
go here we won't have time to cover all
of these
but if people have questions or comments
for me to drill in on each of these
different things
or some of these i can i can do so
yeah um so start throwing your questions
in the chat
i'll warm peter up with one um
[Music]
you know the meme that people are
talking about in the sense making space
is the meaning crisis
i was wondering if you can kind of frame
all this within that
yes the meaning crisis um
the meaning crisis is complex because it
comes from a number
of um it comes from a a number of
different
there's a number of things feeding into
the meeting crisis in my view
one of them is uh is economic in nature
and the nature of uh the way that the
job
situation the the the employment and
economic situation has
unfolded a lot of people participate in
a modern
industrial or post-industrial um
world where our
work is is rather separated from
um the act of production is separate
from the act of use or consumption
and this is not something mcluhan talked
about but this is something a related
topic
that um a guy named gilbert simondon
wrote a lot about
um so the fact that our work is
separated from
the impact of the work um so often
like uh nowadays that's really a
big part of the meaning crisis i think
another part of the meaning crisis
however is directly tied to this which
is that
um we we all each of us have a fine
amount of attention every day
and and more and more that attention is
coupled into systems
that are hierarchical broadcast kind of
in nature
and they um do not encourage us to
engage
in um in sort of convivial
and deeply uh rich interactions with
other people
so uh ironically of course i'm
broadcasting to all of you here in this
thing but
but forgive me for that but um but i
think that is the
that i think is a big part of it as well
uh it's it's shocking if you think um
and i don't know how to speak to you
know the really much younger people
but anyone you know kind of my
generation or maybe maybe a little bit
younger and certainly any older
um before the smartphone which remember
was only 2007 time frame
what did we do all day like we actually
just looked at stuff and thought about
stuff we'd read books we talked to each
other
if we sat around a room by ourselves all
the time uh we get kind of bored we
don't seek other people out hey what are
you doing let me follow along let me
talk a little hey you want to play some
cards
let's or probably end up happening is we
flip on the tv and sit and watch tv
together but at least
we would be together observing a thing
which is
a way to build trust and meaning uh
mutual appreciation of our observation
of a thing
um you know movie night ever watching
movie together at least we all did it
together now movie night is everyone on
the on screen
uh completely atomized from everyone
else in each each getting our own bit
and slice of the giant
um pile of content right so meaning
comes a lot of the meaning for humans
come from
uh interactions with each other and
living in embodied life our interaction
with the environment and the greater
ecology
so much of our technology has been
oriented towards
carving that away and giving us narrow
cast and also a very narrow
um filtered lens on reality
and ultimately meaning suffers so
yeah great uh so we've got tons of
questions in the chat i gotta have to
circle back to that
terror information uh or information
terror complex
that's that's intriguing me but um uh
anjon if you can uh
read your question to peter
hey peter um i was just wondering if you
could give more examples
um for this set of mental models how you
kind of apply them
for this set of mental models how i
apply them um
yes so
for instance you know right now there is
a um a lot of conversation
um after the movie the social dilemma
came out there's now you know a bunch of
twitter and sort of stirred up some
conversation around um
um uh fault and around harm
around these platforms and are they bad
are they good
um you know this and that and the other
and uh and i i read
i can i can get about halfway through
any of those kinds of threads because by
by halfway through
i feel like just like throwing a brick
through my monitor because people are
starting
on this problem from such a broken
metaphysical frame
um and it's like if you were to be
transported back to the 1400s
and you'll walk around and see people
are arguing about whether or not
which kind of leeches are the best to
bleed people out
when they have i don't know a common
cold right and you're like no
probably like stop defecating in the
street that might be a good start right
um and you just feel like tearing your
your your your hair out
because people are coming at this from
the wrong frame
so one material way that this influences
my thinking is understanding that
the thing we have to fix is kind of this
you know mcluhan s
sort of thing uh or this john perry
barlow thing we have to fix the medium
of interaction itself
it's not about putting more fact
checkers on facebook or
regulating the crap out of cda230
although we do need to put some tweaks
on cda230
there's um it's it's really about
the the if the problem see with this
frame you can see the problem is in
creating
a hierarchical system of messaging
communications
creating a disembodied view of sender
and receiver
if we actually privilege the act of
receiving
as an important act that takes that
deserves its own time
and deserves its own space and the
people doing that deserve their own
space
you can design software better you can
criticize and critique
the current stuff from a more i think a
deeper more meaningful way
so tied to that answer then i'll talk
about um this one thing here twitter
and facebook as a shout box so it is
from this frame
that i um came up with a a metaphor for
what facebook is
um which is uh and i'll share with you
all right now which is basically imagine
if you go to
a party uh your friends say hey this is
amazing rave that's going on
it's at this warehouse down you know on
the other side of town
you go over there you walk into this
like warehouse it's got a lot of cars in
the parking lot you go in
and and your eardrums start bleeding
because it is so
loud in there just every because
everyone is walking around
with a 50 watt megaphone to their mouths
and so everyone and the
and the the the speakers are everywhere
there's just like there's the nike
branded and the coca-cola brand and the
pepsi brand and the trump branded
speakers all over the ceiling in there
literally
your heart is like pounding and thumping
like this so as soon as you walk in
the the the kind um uh
you know the people at the door give you
really really amazing headphones uh
and they're noise blocking noise
cancelling and they have a little
friendly f
you know a little facebook blue uh logo
on the outside it's the facebook
headphones and they filter out all of it
except for the few friends you came to
the party with you're like oh this is
awesome
i can see the party it's great and now i
can just hear from my friends
and then every now and then of course
you get a sponsored ad you get a sponsor
a little blurb hey be sure to drink coke
or i guess you would be drinking coke or
drinking beer whatever or mixed drinks
or doing whatever else
there um but but that is
i call it a shout box because the
problem there
is they destroyed the memetic
environment
right no one asked them to to give
everybody megaphones you got a megaphone
too by the way when you go into facebook
and you type anything into a box
on facebook and you hit enter if you
have you know a few hundred friends or
whatever
um all of them by all rights should see
that
the only reason they don't is because
the facebook algorithm comes down and
clamps and
trashes most of the stuff that you type
and only shows your friends what it
wants to show them because they're also
wearing
the the ear the facebook ear muffs so
creating these shout boxes and creating
this really noisy
quote unquote informational environment
that is an intentional act no one asked
them to do that
right how many of you have ever given a
talk to a in-person
audience of a few hundred people right i
have about um
28 000 followers on twitter i've only
ever been in a room with about 3 000
people
right and getting up in stage in front
of a few thousand people like i'm i'm
cool with that because i'm pretty used
to public speaking now
for most people it's a pretty
nerve-wracking experience and certainly
it was for me the first time i did it
but getting on stage in front of 10 10
000 28 000 people i would never do that
but do i think twice we're tweeting
someone say no i don't
right and so the shout box is one of
these things
it's a way to look at the the this
technology
instead of looking at is just a tweak on
you know an internet tweak on broadcast
television
viewing it as a harm or as an
engineering harmful engineering for the
memetic environment
that's a way i can look at it when i
view um communication not in this model
but more in the mcluhan or the the
barlow sense of the thing
and the harm then is articulated as
you're not giving people agency they
cannot tweak the dials on their
facebook and twitter earmuffs they can't
it's the app the app is what the app is
right facebook shut down all of the
different apps that were kind of playing
with their graph api and things like
that
that would offer an alternative
experience to the facebook system they
shut that down you know 10 years ago
so anyway these this one concrete
example
of how i applied this model in my
thinking and my critique of the modern
social media technology
all right um andy you had a question
just turned myself off mute so i'm
thinking metacognitively peter about
this whole process of kind of a 30
person small group
stoa group that's essentially lecture
based but
is uh um supposed to be
i guess in an ideal world if it was a
dance or jazz improvisation
it would be back and forth where the
receivers give
some kind of feedback in real time
to the lecturer and then the lecturer
can adjust accordingly
the content uh do you have some ideas
about how we could make
this process um
ether technology or some other creative
means
um more interactive without
interruption where you're getting the
vibe from the receivers
um yeah that's
uh it's it's a little um that's a good
that's a great question
i mean a lot of this is my own fault
right i could have come in here and just
had a conversation with different people
and just kind of rotate through everyone
calling everyone and we all just have a
you know we have a multiple of 30x
one-on-one right and everyone gets some
value from that that'll be a very
different
mode and feel than me coming here taking
half the time
with uh with a you know a slide deck um
but i felt like presenting some of these
ideas
was part of like the the best way for me
to do some level set or context setting
um and then and it's so it's a trade-off
it's a balance
um uh i think that
if people um the question you ask is
actually the
the most important question um with the
tools and technology
we have how can we create modes of
interaction
that uh are that that best
surface collective intelligence that get
the best questions out
that then create the most the most
insight for the most people etc etc
and then um that that interrupt viewing
that is an interactive process
um you know that is something i don't
know there's a perfect thing out there
at all
i do think but but just consider if
there were no chats at all
if there was no chat and people had to
raise their hand
and then one person let's say it was
peter or somebody else had to go and
pick and call on people
um that's the way that a normal lecture
happens that's the way that talks at
conferences go right
way worse way worse and what i've always
seen in the chat here
is that as people start raising
questions or asking questions or making
additional points
other people start kind of an ad hoc
fashion talking to them
now unfortunately with zoom the chat is
not threaded
and discord also is not threaded i mean
slack is threaded right
but you can imagine not too far in the
future a system where we could have
these interactive dialogues and then the
threaded conversations could actually be
tied to certain time points in the
recording
and anyone going back in time could
watch as they watch recording
the particular parts of the conversation
could actually scroll through
alongside the recording so you can see
what the audience had to say to decorate
it
right um and so
to the point about memory being an
important part
the medium has memory the memory can
influence the nature of the
communication itself
at that point being there live for this
event is almost
ancillary it's because you can always
come afterwards and see
the text and then add another comment
and then we can have a conf i mean i
would still be able to be tagged right
and i'd have to be able to have a
conversation and this would be a much
richer
sort of thing especially if those things
could
easily link to nodes and notion or roam
or whatever
you just build this like actual
sense-making uh
technology web that will be really rich
and powerful
um you know there's it's really hard to
solve the
the fundamental live interaction
bandwidth problem um because humans just
understand language at a certain rate
um and there's there's a trade-off to
like having a small group of five or six
people who can each get equal airtime
to getting to amplifying you know having
many people be able to get in real time
but but even even then we see that
there's panel discussions with audiences
that can participate right
so those are also ways to to kind of
expand the medium i think any point
any way you choose to do live kind of
things like this
it's always a trade-off um but i think
tying it to both memory and tying it to
a higher um more featureful kind of
textual mechanism to tie in everyone
else's brains
who are part of the thing that's what
ultimately is going to crew you know
cause this thing to be much more
powerful
all right danny you had a question
you're gonna mute yourself
it was about um what was it about it
again
here we go now yeah i mean there you go
i have for years been haunted
by how much i want to share
information i hear it and it's like this
thrust it's like it's not it's not
enough for me to know it i want to be
sharing it
yes yeah and that's getting accelerated
right and then the other side of it is
i'm getting deluged by
all the sharing that's happening and i
can't remember
if i saw some place in one of your talks
where you said some you said
sharing is knowledge or something like
that
did you make a connection between
sharing and knowledge i don't remember
anyway i i just want to know what your
how do you feel because certainly it
work it's all about twitter and
everything you know that's what we're
doing we're
sharing so what do you think about
sharing
oh yeah um i think sharing i mean maybe
it was in this
session on um well three was temporal
and
two was relational right and would have
had to be
in relational that i would have said um
yeah dynamic relationships and then the
uh all right yeah i couldn't find it
again it's just sort of
it's a piece of this that you know the
meaning making but there's something
about it that's still
broadcasting right when i share i'm kind
of broadcasting
well you don't have to
um and and i think uh let me open up
this one and um
let me share share screen in a broadcast
fashion
uh oh so meta oh so deliciously meta
okay uh this one
and it may have been either um probably
not this slide
but maybe um i think
maybe on the section on privacy
here or
here no well i mean i guess the thing i
would say is that
sharing is not the same as broadcast and
um a little bit to peter's question
about um
the the meaning crisis we are all
enrolled in unfortunately a sense of
the uh viral fame lottery in celebrity
culture ever since the emergence of
elect
sort of these electric broadcast things
in the uh in the early
20th century um so fame culture the
celebrity stardom
all these other kinds of things um in
the democratization of that
sort of pseudo-democratization of that
with reality television
um and uh and whatnot um
we are all enrolled unfortunately
against our will into a famed culture
and that same culture
the entire engine of hollywood all of
the advertising budgets across the
around
the world they all fuel this dynamic to
make
us to hack our social and our
psychological and our emotional selves
um to want to be part of that it's it's
like how do you take the middle school
cafeteria and make it like metastasize
that across the entire world
and raise it to the power of a
kardashian right and so like
that is essentially the the world we
live in
and so you can't help but be like drawn
sucked into the gravity the the
emotional and psychic gravity
of of a famed celebrity culture of
broadcast
of um i guess paul simon greatly you
know beautifully put it as every
generation sends a hero up the pop
charts
right um it's uh that dynamic though
let's be very clear there is nothing in
it for you
it does not make meaning for you it does
not help you be in right relationship
with anything
at the very best it can be identified as
something
that gives us um uh maybe gives us a bit
of serendipitous connection with other
people who may be
of similar values to us like oh i like
i like kim kardashian you like him good
as you maybe have something in common we
can go actually have a convivial
relationship together and be
friends but probably not right because
that's not the point of kim kardashian
that's not the point of celebrities and
celebrity images
and celebrity culture the point of it is
to move product schlep a bunch of
product and create
a neurotic desire to consume so when we
think about sharing
i want to go back to the more primal
almost shamanistic
view of sharing which is sharing is
sharing is is giving sharing is loving
right
if it's a sharing that's not rooted in
loving if there's no
there there to love if there's no one
there to put that into
then then then the sharing is your shot
you're throwing a dart at the celebrity
dartboard
and that's that's just kind of what it
is right i'm here and all of you are
here and i appreciate it i'm when i say
thank you for showing up and
giving your time and attention i really
do mean it um even though i only see
you know the words from some of you uh
you know i put my time into doing this
because i care about it because i hope
that
some of the things i'm saying are
meaningful for for you all and help you
you know make better sense of the world
and i do that purely out of love i do it
out of no no other thing than that
um and all of us can live life that way
all of us can choose to stop
and not and just kind of get off the
train of wanting to have viral explosion
and just say
i'm gonna have a meaningful interaction
with this person today and no one else
in the world will ever know about it i'm
just doing this
but this is meaningful to me and it's
meaningful to them and
in that and that's the thing that i
would say that that's really been taken
away from us
is the notion that we have agency
and we we have the ability to make our
own meaning we don't have to just
do it by signing up for something we can
make meaning with other people
all day long every day it's just on us
and and and danny to your thing about
wanting to share
i think you'll find just as as uh the
great um
um oh my god uh tom lehrer said life is
like a sewer what you get it what you
get out of what you put it depends on
what you put into it
so if you if you put into uh those that
sharing
not a not a desire to have things go
viral or be famous or whatever
but out of a like an authentic genuine
desire to participate in a conversation
you'll find probably a lot of haters a
lot of people ignore you but then a few
people connect and you just work those
connections
um i think you'll find that you get a
great deal of meaning and pleasure out
of that
and i think that's that that's the thing
when jordan talks about the
self-organizing collective intelligence
uh the reason why jordan like is so
so fascinated with q anon as a thing is
that there is a pu
not necessarily their ideas but q anon
is a phenomenon let's be very clear
um there is a very interesting thing
about
how networked it is it's like the web
rings of 20 years ago
when people made websites and they found
a few other people who are willing to
babylon 5 are really into anime
and they connected with them that was
meaningful that was a meaningful web
it wasn't a great web for facebook to go
make trillions of dollars on but it was
a meaningful web for human
collective kind of collective network
meaning making
so i don't know if that answers your
question but that was just you know
speaking to the point i guess about
yeah let me um let me reflect one thing
is
to pause for me to pause why am i
sharing
where is it coming from
and then this the last thing you said
and i would even say just a meaning
web rather than meaning full web a
meaning
web if that's what
my what my um motive is
yes yes yeah and and the thing is that
of course if you try to do it by
yourself in the middle of the shout box
you're you're going to be drowned out so
you need to find places
and be adjacent to places and people and
groups
where you're more likely to find people
who will interact with you in this way
right we need to surf into the little
title uh title pools
of serendipitous connection and from
there create
more and more um richly connected kind
of webs of meaning
so i think that's kind of how we have to
cultivate this uh i'm personally
invested in some technology
to create better infrastructure that
gets us to
getting serendipity and modern web kinds
of things but away and
outside of the shoutbox monetization
system
and i think those kinds of things will
uh dramatically
improve uh the ability of people like
yourself and others like you
who want to find these kinds of
connections and do this kind of sharing
that is generative as opposed to just
having it all washed away by the
facebook
shoutbox right so yeah
cool uh peter we're at the hour do you
have time for one more question
i do yes absolutely cool uh def you have
uh dief i should say you have a question
you can ask it um
oh which one um whatever one feels alive
for you
i like the topic and it's something that
i've been diving hacking into but
a lot of times the mental models
sometimes
it i have to attract the audience and
the audience sometimes they have to give
the audience where they are yeah and
maybe one of the muscles i've built
doing zoom is that
i find zoom uh talking to the void
there's an emptiness of just this
platform just
it's crap because it's just this tasting
and timing of interaction
it's just a non-human so
uh one aspect is a question of building
this muscle
tracking the flow of the audience and
just the pace of
communication flow and then is there
a mechanism of uh facilitating better so
that
you have curators editors
filters who can help process all the
shouting to say
this is what five of the shelters are
saying or this is
this is just noise over here someone who
some level of intelligence instead of ai
which is just advertising
let's say and then also digital media
there's a framing of analog versus
digital
so digital allows you to compress time
you just take out all the excess but
then that's not
human you're processing too much digital
versus human analog take whatever you
want that response
um so i think there's oh yeah so number
one
um you you can actually i was gonna say
you could use some
modern machine learning kinds of things
to do
um condensation of a lot of textual
feedback
and then maybe like you know kind of net
that out and try to like
give the uh the speaker sort of like top
level things like here are the things
that people liked and what you said like
uh a dream system if one were to dream
is one that captures my
my speech and transcribes it in real
time and then
it looks at that looks what people are
speaking to responding to and then it
does
some i don't know gpt three-ish kinds of
things
to go and net out okay here's what the
what people are responding to this last
two slides you just presented right
here's a couple of the the more popular
questions that people had
that would that you can absolutely build
a
you know with what we have today you
could sort of build some something kind
of like that i think
uh although it would take some tweaking
um but something like that in the future
could be very useful
for doing this compression and
integration right of of a broad
number of people when we're speaking in
zoom there is definitely a sense of
um we are speaking into the void
what one thing that's that's interesting
i would i would i would be curious
what different speakers views are when
they're speaking
so i tend to prefer to have a gallery
mode
so that i can see um what i'm doing when
i'm doing meetings with like my
my senior executives or whatever i
provide gallery mode because then i can
see everyone i can see kind of
people's resp expressions and i'm sort
of looking at that just like if we're in
a small room together
when it starts to get to quite a large
number of people though uh when i do
like um you know conference keynote or
whatever like that
i switch to um speaker view
so i'm actually just seeing myself and
um and that may seem really weird but
it's it's uh it's almost like my brain
fragments into two
and there's a part of me that's like
like a qa supervisor
that's looking at how i'm showing up and
trying to play based on what i know the
audience
or what i think of the audience it's
trying to play back how they're
receiving
my thing so i'm doing real-time
modulation of
of my um of my speech of how i show up
of my
my cadence and things like that uh it's
not an intel it's not a
a a a conscious process even it's
it actually makes me feel very
comfortable to be talking to my own
image i don't know what that says of me
but but i i like it because then
well it's like a studio monitor right
when you're singing you want to have the
monitor so you can hear yourself
it's it's that kind of thing um but
you're right
i mean when you do a zoom presentation
it's you're speaking to the void
and and that's so different than being
an audience of real people because you
get the energy of people people nodding
people you just look around everyone's
checking their phones or people holding
up
my favorite when i give technical talks
when people hold up their cell phones
take pictures of my slides
that's great um so so you're always
reading the real-time
dynamics of the room and the whole body
the embodied experience of that
is very different because you feel like
you're actually in this room of people
you're in a connected web even if
they're not saying a single word
and that's your point about analog
versus digital um now i don't know that
the word analog versus digital is the is
the the words that i would choose but i
know exactly what you mean by what
you're demarcating with with that split
which is that the full spectrum
interaction that we get
versus the things that we tend to
digitize which is you know audio
and this many rectangular pixels of
video and that's it
right um and that's actually a very
impoverished um
down sample of the the full spectrum
uh reality well also throw into this
sound is sort of just killed in the
digital medium there's a biased
visual what do you mean
the compression of sound takes out the
3d
nature of sound oh yes our ears can hear
like 10 miles away or
very far but just the digital medium
kills that the nuance and richness of
sound there is a tremendous amount of
there's
the other thing is since we're all on
zoom you only see me from the chest up i
could be
naked from the waist down right now none
of you would even know right um
so the the the whole body language
i try to be live on zoom calls i try to
have just sit back enough to where i can
gesticulate and you at least see my like
shoulder and head
kind of things but when we're in person
we
you know people cross arms people yawn
and stretch people you know like they
slouch they do all sorts of things
there's a lot of body language involved
that is completely lost in the zoom
culture as well so
yeah um
cool um so we're going to close out here
before we do i wanted to double click on
the um
what was that called information terror
complex oh yeah sure
i got time if you all have time um
so it's uh the good the good news about
the information terror complex
is that it is actually a blog post i've
written a medium
and my point in the blog post was just
um
in fact let's if i google for it
that doesn't actually come up very much
i'm probably am i the only person who's
actually used that term no
oh yeah no that's the uh that's my blog
post okay
so i'm i am the a-hole who um
who popularized this concept here i are
not popularized clearly i didn't
popularize it
um my point on this was that um
it is the dissemination
um so i said this i said look it's
here's the thing
you know how when people when there's
like some kind of suicide attack or some
kind of thing like that or there's a
terror attack
um they'll say oh well we're not giving
we're not we're not like the media will
say we're not gonna you know
glamorize the the killer or whatever
else we don't want to have so we have we
don't want to have copycat attacks
they sort of recognize that media itself
has a role to play in this stuff
um and i said look the quickest way to
actually destroy terrorism
as a tool would be to institute a
blanket news media policy
a total blackout regarding terrorist
attacks and so
um because my point is that an actual
terror attack
only kills a few people uh i mean it
sucks for those people and their
families like i'm not trying to
trivialize the tragedy of it
i mean even 911 it killed thousands of
people but
what creates terrorism is the
dissemination of information
the information impact the medium the
way the medium transmits and shocks
everyone
that is actually that dissemination of
information
creates the state of terror among the
population
so you can say well the jihadists that
crashed the planes into the buildings of
they created a lot of corpses and mass
death they destroyed
they killed people they're murderers of
the highest degree
but to say they're terrorists they
wouldn't be terrorist by themselves
without the global information system
amplifying
and then writing a lot of additional
narrative on top of that
to create a state of terror this is a
really really
weird statement in a sense but i would
say it's kind of incontrovertible
right and i said look if you look at the
um
the the uh what is what i'm called the
guy the jihadi john or whatever
he goes and he cuts somebody's throat
you know he slits somebody is in this
like execution
um you know over in the other side of
the world for most of us it's like
okay he killed a person a lot of people
get killed all the time in those in that
part of the world
i mean well everywhere in the world but
why that one is an act of terrorism it's
an act of terrorism because the entire
media establishment
and all of our our mechanisms for
so-called sense making
zoom into that and create they induce a
sense of terror
and fear among the population so
my my statement was that our modern
information dissemination structures
themselves amplify the act
and they weave into the fabric of our
national story and we call it journalism
we call it news reporting
whatever but the susceptibility
to creating terrorism or a terrorism
dynamic or creating terror in the people
is actually a property of that kind of
news media environment
so this is to the earlier question um
from who by the question of how do i use
this mental framework or these cognitive
models
to understand the world this is one of
those examples when you actually go and
perceive the medium
and you perceive the act of the medium
itself in a susceptibility
and the way that it is um sort of hacked
by certain kinds of things that cause it
to go into shock
um when you can perceive the medium then
you can see oh wait
the medium is at fault the medium is
actually
well not at fault but the medium is a
part of the dynamic
so that's why i called the information
terrorism complex i said this
vulnerability
when it's exploited by jihadist groups
creates the standing wave pattern which
is this fear of random acts of violence
right
um and so and i had this line there by
terrorism terrorism by definition
is the creation of a state of fear
hysteria among a population and last i
checked
isis doesn't operate any radio towers
here in the united states
right it is all of the media
establishment that operates the media
that the
isis kills people the media creates
terror creates a state of terror
and um anyway that's that's just uh
that was what that was all about
yeah that's cool um i really like that
meme it
makes me want to explore like humane
tech here at the store and all these
type of uh movements that tristan harris
and others are working on
um so let's land the plane here uh
peter any closing thoughts for for this
session of the series as a whole yes let
me um let me just share this one last
thing here which
is i do have i did actually put a
conclusion slide in believe it or not
so last thoughts here so to net it all
out inverse your metaphysics
replace the atomicized object-oriented
cartesian model
with superpositional right everything
you think of a solid physical reality
um it's actually the quantization or the
reduction of a continuous relationship
um of these non-atomized things so learn
to see the world in that
in that way time is perceptual and it's
driven by frequency and attention
don't think of time as just like some
like einsteinian fourth dimension and
all this other nonsense
just actually the r general time the way
you interact with time probably for the
rest of your life
it's actually more driven by frequency
and attention than by any other dynamic
and space is relational space is not
just meter sticks and yardsticks
space is actually especially in the
electric age
it's it's relational distance is defined
by our sense of context and control
so um so yeah think about space and time
in those ways
and again identity is not atomic either
it's not cartesian identity
it's this tension between our inner
selves and motivations the external
social
and the medic and environmental field
around us and lastly
which today's session and i guess i
didn't quite talk about this topic
but i talked all around it which is
information is not
a noun information is not an artifact or
the static thing
information is a verb that's that's a
line i stole straight from
um from from john perry barlow and i
guess um
gregory bateson information is a verb it
is the act of sense making
so let's not think about transmitting
information let's think about helping
people do better informationing
so that is what i leave all of you
wonderful people with
beautiful so uh we'll close out here
peter thanks so much uh
for today and thank you to stoa as a
sense-making resident that's a lovely
series uh
i quite enjoyed it and the buzz i got
from it people enjoyed it as well
uh so thank you and we'd love to have
you back uh maybe in a couple months uh
from maybe another around um yeah
interaction with other people
um consider the stoa a home a digital
home thank you i appreciate it so much
and i'll try to be on discord a little
more than i have been
lately but thank you all so much for for
your attention and
uh share widely encoura you know reach
out to me on twitter
um and uh and get others to to you know
just
there's so i'm just i'm just stealing
everyone else's ideas here and so
lots of other great thinkers that have a
lot of good stuff in this area um
ping me for for references and whatnot
if you if you want so thank you all very
much
beautiful beautiful so uh um
yeah we have a few sessions today um
that's so cool uh deep has a bunch of
people clapping on his
zoom thing um yeah so we have a
collective presence coming up in about
45 minutes
uh we have a socratic social coming up
at 7 00
p.m eastern time tonight just to kind of
chill with the store village
uh next week i'll plug this event um the
pandemic of group think
uh young in the collective shadow uh
there's this character uh
irish guy on youtube uh uber uber boyo
uh he's coming in september 28th 12 p.m
eastern time i think that's monday you
can rsvp there
um and if you like to support us on
patreon
uh while we get some mental models on
during this meta crisis you can do so
there
that being said peter everyone thanks
for coming to stowa today thank you all
very much